视频全程多次提到核动力火箭、阿波罗工程
相关视频请看视频说明
最近马一龙的SpaceX打算去火星的事尽人皆知
With all the talk of manned Mars missions by Elon Musk and SpaceX
NASA也在搞，但很少有人知道去火星这事其实很久以前就有人提了
and more recently NASA it's easy to forget that Mars isn't a recent obsession
在开唠之前，先说一句，这期视频不太一样
Now before we get into the details, this video is a little different
因为这是我第一次和别人合作的视频，另一半由Isaac Arthur制作
because this is my first collaboration and part two of this series will be done by Isaac Arthur
他会从90年代科幻作品的内容讲起
who will be looking at the Mars missions from the roots of sci-fi in the
因为那段时间关于火星的内容开始兴起
1990s to those which are proposed for the coming decades
给虫对科幻作品不太了解，应该不会做字幕，但在视频说明里有YouTube链接
There's a link in the description that will take you there directly and if you've come over from Isaac's channel
而如果你从那个视频来，那么欢迎来到Curious Droid频道，欢迎观看关于人类
welcome to Curious Droid, and the first part of the manned
在阿波罗之后早有规划但胎死腹中的火星任务
Mars missions that were planned for the post Apollo period but never got off the ground
我也建议你们在咱的频道转转
and I hope you can take a little time to have a look around this channel
如果喜欢视频，欢迎点赞投币收藏分享关注一波
and also some of you have our videos and hopefully like and subscribe
如果你们没听过、没看过Isaac的频道，我也推荐你们去看看
Now if you haven't heard or seen Isaac's channel then I recommend you hop on over there
因为这期视频是他那期的知识背景
after you've watched this of course because this is a kind of sets up for his video
但他的视频更偏向科幻、未来主义
but his channel deals with the science and futurism and covers a whole
里面有很多我从来没想过的方面
load of things that I've never even thought of
让我眼前一亮、醍醐灌顶，如果你喜欢远科幻、大尺度的科普内容的话，强烈推荐
but I found highly informative and very entertaining, well worth a visit if you like your futurism on the grand scale
自从齐奥尔科夫斯基、戈达德、奥伯特、埃斯诺-佩尔特里这些人
Ever since Konstantin Tsiolkovsky, Robert Goddard, Hermann Oberth and Robert Esnault-Pelterie discovered the
在20世纪早期发现了火箭、航天的基本定律
principles of rocketry and Astronautics in the early twentieth century
我们一直打算去火星，即使那年代这更像是听上去
we've been planning on going to Mars though back then it was much more of an academic
贼科幻的学术问题
issue with a large dose of science fiction
但在冯·布劳恩40年代还在给德国人干活时就搞出V2导弹了以后
But with the development of a V2 rocket led by Verna von Braun whilst he was working for Germans in the 1940s
太空旅行的可能性就很大了
the possibility of space travel became a reality
1948年冯·布劳恩跑到美国造火箭的时候
By 1948 when Von Braun was working for the US developing its rocket capability
他出版了一本书叫《火星计划》
he'd published a book called the Mars Project
这可能是人类火星任务到目前为止最有影响力的书了
this has become probably the most influential book on the subject of manned Mars missions
即使书中计划是十艘飞船载70人，比马一龙的PPT还牛逼
even though it was a rather grandiose scheme which called for a fleet of 10 spacecraft carrying 70 or more people
冯·布劳恩当时的想法是，如果当年哥伦布只用一艘船发现了新大陆
Von Braun used the idea that if Columbus had set off to find the new world with just a single ship
那他就够呛能回西班牙了
and he would probably have never made it back to Spain
尽管冯的书略有科幻成分，但书中
Although his book was looked upon as Sci-fi by some, von braun provided detailed
冯给出了很多详细的计算来支撑他的想法
calculations to support his theories and many of the ideas he put forward
而书中还有很多诸如“可重复使用航天飞机”、“在轨组装”、“多飞船编队”的理念
like reusable shuttles, orbital assembly and multiple spacecraft have greatly
也影响着NASA的长期星际载人任务计划
influenced nasa's long-term plans for manned interplanetary missions
即使没书里写的那么夸张了
even if they have been greatly cut down in scale
冯在书中还提到了人类在去火星的路上会遇到的问题，比如失重对人体的影响
He also covered the main problems of getting men to Mars, such as the effect of weightlessness on the human body
太阳与宇宙辐射、在一艘飞船失效时利用太空行走从一个飞船
radiation from a Sun and cosmic rays, using spacesuits to move from one ship
转移到另一个飞船，还有长期居住在密闭空间内的心理影响
to another if one were to be disabled and also the psychological effects of
having people live in enclosed space for long periods of time
早在五六十年代大家就都知道，如果是搞航天
Back in the 1950s and 60s there was still the belief that if you're going to
那要搞的事可不少，就像光阿波罗计划前前后后就有四十万人参与
go and do a space mission then you go big. Just like Apollo was a huge effort employing around 400,000 people
而当时美苏两家也基本都在研究怎么去火星
The Mars proposals from both the US and the Soviets were equally large
尤其当时民族自尊心强、副产物还是先进武器
especially when national pride was at stake and the spin-off was a range of new advanced weapons
苏联那边对抗土星五号的是N1超级烟花
In the Soviet Union their answer of Saturn V, the ill-fated N1 rocket had actually been designed by
它实际上是科罗廖夫在50年代设计用来载人去火星的
Sergey Korolyov in the 1950s to launch a manned Mars mission
人类第一次正式的火星计划是由前苏联工程师吉洪拉沃夫带头的
The first serious Mars planning done by the Soviets was headed by Mikhail Tikhonravov in 1956
名字叫MPK(Martian火星的Piloted有人控制的Complex复合体)
and was known as the MPK or Martian Piloted Complex
计划30个月的任务，在火星表面着陆
This would have a crew on a 30-month mission to land on the Martian surface
在表面呆一年多，然后返回
and stay there for just over a year before returning
毛子的这个计划里甚至还有核动力火星火车
There were even plans for a nuclear-powered Mars train
五个模块构成，打算在火星表面飙车
to be made up of five modules which would travel across the Martian surface
1959年，OKB-1设计局的一个团队开始了
By 1959 a group within the OKB-1 design bureau had started development
星际飞船TMK的研发，打算载三人
of an interplanetary spacecraft called the TMK which was to carry a three-man crew
飞跃火星，并释放一个远程控制的着陆器
for a Mars flyby and drop remote control Landers to the surface
发射时间定为1971年6月8日，三年后返回地球
A launch date was penciled in for June 8th 1971 and returning to Earth over three years later
为了克服失重
电影《2001太空漫游》 拍摄于1968年 强烈推荐
To overcome the effects of weightlessness
TMK最初设计是自转制造人工重力
it was proposed that the TMK would rotate about its axis to create a form of artificial gravity
有点像电影《2011太空漫游》里那个
a bit like the space station in the film 2001
然而由于飞船直径太小，科里奥利力会造成恶心
However because of its small diameter the Coriolis forces created could have induced nausea which
反而还不如失重
would have been worse than the weightlessness itself
辐射这个问题当时也是未知量，但从无人探测器返回的数据来看
Radiation was still an unknown quantity but with data from unmanned probes it was thought that
载人往返火星任务积累的辐射量
the cumulative radiation dose for a return mission to Mars would have been
不考虑太阳耀斑情况下应该是在安全阈值内的
within safe levels but that didn't account for solar flares
所以后来人们提出弄一个管状的防辐射舱
This was to be addressed by having a radiation shelter which was a shielded tube in the center
放在飞船中央，里面放些简单的设备和控制仪器
of a craft with simplified instruments and controls
就算是在五十年代，人们也早就意识到化学火箭的性能
Even as far back as the 1950s it was realized that chemical rockets were just on the verge of
已经接近火星载人任务的极限了
feasibility when trying to get a manned mission to Mars and back again
相比而言核动力火箭则能用更小的质量提供更大的能量
and the nuclear on the other hand would provide greater power with much lower mass
从而在更短的时间内进行地火转移，同时在到达火星后提供电能
making for significantly shorter transit times and the secondary abilities to generate electrical power once at Mars
1954年冯·布劳恩团队的史图林格在看了奥伯特的文章后开始对电推进感兴趣
In 1954 Ernst Stuhlinger who was working on Von Braun's team became interested in electrical propulsion
after reviewing a paper on a subject by Herman J. Oberth
史图林格认为飞船可以设计成在轨道空间有比化学火箭更高的推力
Stuhlinger believed that a spacecraft could be designed that would give greater thrust than a chemical rocket
if it's set off from orbit
核动力电推发动机在科罗廖夫的大力资瓷下成为了星际运输的推进系统
The nuclear electric engine became the interplanetary propulsion system favored by the Soviet chief designer Sergey
主要就是一个核反应堆，给离子电推供电
Korolev, basically a nuclear reactor creating electricity to drive a plasma ion thruster
1962年美国的NASA也开始了EMPIRE计划
By 1962 in the U.S. NASA commissioned the project EMPIRE studies
EMPIRE计划
Early早期 Manned载人 Panetary-Interplanetary行星际
Roundtrip往返 Expeditions考察
来研究人类去火星的路上都需要什么
to look into the human exploration of Mars and what would be required
有三家公司参与：福特航空部(想不到吧)、通用动力、洛克希德导弹与太空部
Three companies were involved Ford's aeronautic division, General Dynamics and Lockheed missiles of space
福特提议两次飞金星、两次飞火星
Ford suggested a dual flyby of both Venus and then onto Mars by launching and arriving
基本能在旅程中点的位置到达火星，一箭双雕
relative to Mars at the midpoint of the interplanetary trajectory, a sort of planetary double-whammy
运载火箭建议使用土星五号、Nova或超级Nova火箭入轨
They suggested using either a Saturn 5, Nova or Supernova rockets to launch into orbit
地火转移用核动力级，在轨机动用化学火箭
and then the nuclear injection stage and chemical rocket maneuvering
整个任务持续21个月，花费大约126亿美元
The whole mission would last around 21 months and cost $12.6 Billion
大约是今天的1000亿美元，包含了运载火箭的开发
around about $100 billion in todays money plus the cost of launch vehicle development
通用动力的解决方案只是一个约8人的火星任务
General Dynamics suggested just a Mars mission with a crew of around about eight
也是使用土星五号加NERVA核动力发动机
and again using a Saturn V and NERVA nuclear engine option
通用动力表示在核动力发动机的帮助下，1973年到1975年之间择机发射
They said that with nuclear engines and an optimal launch date of 1973 to 75 when Mars
火星与地球离的最近的时候，整个任务可以缩短到
would be at its closest approach, the whole mission could be reduced to
400-450天，其中包括30-50天的
400-450 days including a 30-50 day stay in
火星环绕轨道，其间可以进行着陆并采样返回
the Martian orbit with a possible landing and sample return
这需要八发土星五号在轨组装火星任务飞船
The team said that it would require 8 Saturn Vs to assemble a Mars mission vehicle
总载荷在450吨左右
and would have a payload around 450 tons
他们的规划需要十年的时间，从1965年到1975年，花费245亿美元
Their proposal would be over a ten-year period from 1965 to 1975 and cost $24.5 billion
折合今天的1960亿美元
$196 billion in today's money
洛克希德的提议是12人的670天火星任务
Lockheed proposal was for a mission to Mars that would last 670 days for up to a crew of 12
为之后的火星着陆任务“探路”
and will be a precursor to later missions that would land on the Martian surface
仍然使用土星五号加NERVA的组合
Again it would use for Saturn V nuclear NERVA propulsion combination
但有趣的是，洛马的方案中有一个可自转的模块
but one interesting difference here was that the team suggested that a craft rotating at
每分钟自转三周，制造0.4G的重力
three revolutions per minute could generate 0.4g of gravity
从而改善在星际航行中的失重影响
during the interplanetary phase to help offset the effect of weightlessness
和毛子的TMK很像
pretty much like with TMK in the russian solution
虽然EMPIRE计划中的所有提议都只停留在图纸上，该计划却让人类第一次
Although none of the EMPIRE missions moved beyond the initial design phase, it was the first time since the
真正认真讨论了火星项目的细节内容，并把结果分享给整个航天领域
Mars project that detailed proposals were carried out and shared with the rest of a space community
这迟早会说服NASA火星载人任务是可行的
This in time would convince many in NASA that manned missions to Mars were feasible
1969年冯·布劳恩又重新修正了下他的火星计划
By 1969 Von Braun had been refining his own ideas for Mars
冯的最终版本有两艘飞船
His final plans had two ships each with
每艘六人，编队航行，各自除了火星着陆器外都有整套设备
a six-man crew and would fly in a convoy with the entire setup apart from the
可以在未来任务中重复使用
Mars Lander, being able to be reusable for future missions
在登月成功后，人们对未来更多的载人航天任务有了些许热情
After the first moon landings there was a brief enthusiasm for more manned spaceflight
冯·布劳恩把他的载人火星计划作为
Von Braun proposed his vision of a manned Mars mission as
阿波罗计划后续任务的一部分，其中还包括航天飞机
part of a post Apollo integrated plan which included a manned shuttle in its
在1975年的原型，然后是空间站，还有以土星五号作为上升段
original form by 1975, space stations there after, plus continued development of a saturn V as the launch stage
NERVA热核发动机作为上面级的星际旅行任务
and the NERVA nuclear thermal upper stage for the interplanetary part of the journey
这个计划的亮点在于
The beauty of this setup was that the
经过验证的空间站模块可以用于火星任务的居住舱
proven space station modules would be used as the living quarters for the Mars missions
土星五号目前就是一个很好的验证，用能力把组件送进地球轨道
The Saturn V was by now a well proven way to get the main parts into orbit
而NERVA发动机也在地面进行了多次测试，准备好进入太空
and the NERVA nuclear engine had been tested and was ready to be put into space
唯一要新造的就是火星着陆器了
The only new hardware required would be the Mars Lander
其测试最初定于1978年，而火星任务最初定于1982年进行
Testing was envisaged starting in 1978 with the first Mars mission in 1982
然后用航天飞机在轨补给转移飞船
The shuttle would be used to refurbish the Mars craft in space with further missions
使其继续进行1983年、86年、88年的任务，最后在89年建立一个50人的火星基地
planned for 1983, 86 and 88 with a 50-person Mars base by 1989
然而咱们也都知道，事情没按剧本走，NASA高层不想载人飞出月球
However as we know things didn't go according to plan, there was resistance from senior
figures within NASA to manned missions beyond the moon
七十年代初，公众对航天的兴趣减弱，同时越战也花了美国不少钱
By the early 1970s the public's interesting space waned the war in Vietnam was like a political
albatross around the neck of the US government and was costing a fortune
老百姓也不想让国家往太空领域砸那么多的钱
There was little public appetite for more hugely expensive space missions
研究说火星任务要花120到320亿美元
Studies put the cost of a Mars mission between $12 and $32 billion
相当于今天的930到2500亿美元
or between $93 and $250 billion in today's money
火星更像是一个死气沉沉的地方，非常无聊
Mars was seen as a dead and pretty uninteresting place
而后来水手6号、7号的飞跃任务也证实了这一点
which was confirmed rather ironically by the Mariner 7 flyby
非常讽刺的是，飞跃那天刚好是冯·布劳恩1969年给NASA做完火星任务PPT的下一天
the day after Von Braun's big 1969 Mars presentation to NASA
1972年总统换届，即使副总统Spiro Agnew为火星任务作担保
With a change of administration in 1972 and even with vice president Spiro Agnew's endorsement of a Mars mission
尼克松还是大砍NASA经费
Nixon slashed NASA's budget
而阿波罗计划后唯一留下的就是后来一直在用的航天飞机了
and the only thing left of a post Apollo plan was the much repurposed Space Shuttle and the
还有一次土星五号发射的天空实验室空间站
leftover Saturn V rockets which were used for the Skylab space station
而非土星五号不可的NERVA发动机也就此夭折
The NERVA nuclear engine which was so reliant upon the post Apollo plan was also scrapped
毛子那边N1四次大烟花
In the Soviet Union the failure to produce a workable N1 rocket and with
还有类似美国的财政问题，他们那的火星项目也无限延期
similar economic issues to the US the Soviet Mars projects were also shelved indefinitely
作为N1的替代——能源号火箭在上世纪七十年代中期到八十年代
With the development of the N1's replacement the giant Energia rocket in the mid 1970s and 80s
加上苏联的暴风雪号航天飞机，苏联曾经重拾了一丢丢对火星任务的兴趣
and the Soviet Space Shuttle Buran there was a brief flurry of interest in Mars missions once more
但在苏联解体后，能源号火箭
but after the collapse of a Soviet Union both the Energia rocket
和仅存的火星任务也都GG了
and the remaining ideas for Mars missions were also shelved
尽管后来几十年有一些成功的无人任务
Although there were successful robotic missions to Mars in the following decades
八九十年代载人任务也被那些顽固的行星科学家和爱好者限制了
interest in manned missions in the 1980s and 90s was limited to the die-hard planetary scientists and enthusiasts
甚至连科幻作品在这段时间都把火星无视了
Even sci-fi gave up on Mars during this time
因为公众对火星的兴趣逐渐减少，而我们这期视频也差不多到这了
as it slipped from much of a public's consciousness and this is where our part one of the story ends
下半部分你们请看Isaac的SFIA频道吧
And we hand you over to Isaac's SFIA channel for part two of the series
然而我们说的只是九牛一毛
However we aren't quite done yet
在当年各种计算都是徒手完成的时候
The logistics of planning a mission as complex as sending
计划这样一个送人类火星往返的超大工程难度是无法想象的
men to Mars back in the day where most of the working out was done with a slide rule is truly amazing
就像阿波罗工程一样，把上千位科学家
Just like Apollo it would have been a massive undertaking bringing together thousands of scientists
工程师、数学家凑在一起，去完成这项伟大工程，简直难以想象
engineers and mathematicians, and is truly incredible to imagine the full complexity of the operation
后面就是赞助商的广告时间了……字幕翻译给虫，喜欢记得点赞投币分享收藏关注一波
To begin to get a grasp of how these things working in the trenches
you might start small for instance how fast must we launch an object from the
surface of the earth to get into space you can look up the answer if you want
but if you like me you want to create things yourself. Our sponsor for this
collaboration brilliant.org is dedicated
to just that, turning you into a living breathing and most importantly
calculating scientist. Head over there and prove for yourself just what it
takes to get an object up and off of a plate and headed towards a new home like
Mars. Having a strong math and science skills set is crucial because it opens
up so many ways to explore the universe. To support curious droid and to learn
more about brilliant go to brilliant.org/curiousdroid and sign up
for free. Also if you're ready to launch off of a planet the first 200 people
will get 20% discount off of the annual premium subscription.